<section title="Introduction to the World of ELinks">
<t>

	The goal of this introduction is to explain the basic concepts
	in ELinks, give an overview of how to get started and serve as
	an entry point to many of the (undocumented) features of ELinks.
	It won't tell you all the details, but should hopefully give you
	an idea of how things work and make it possible for you to even
	figure out how to go further.

</t>
<t>

	Allthough ELinks is text-based, the user interface has many of
	interaction methods normally found in graphical environments.
	There are menus, dialogs with buttons and hierarchic list boxes
	with folders. Care has been taken to make the interaction
	between various dialogs consistent, so the controls will quickly
	become familiar to new users.

</t>
<t>

	The user interface can be controlled using both mouse and
	keyboard, but currently it is only possible to configure
	keybindings. Looking back, the key-controls have been more
	advanced than the mouse support, but during the 0.10 prereleases
	the mouse support has been much improved. You will now find find
	stuff like contextual menus when right-clicking in different
	document zones.

</t>

<section title="Overview of the User Interface">
<t>

	The main user interface of ELinks consists of the document view
	and dialog bars displaying the information such as the title of
	the currently viewed document, all opened tabs and the browsing
	status. The 3 bars are elaborated further below.

</t>
<t>

	The most important dialogs that you will meet include the Main,
	Link and Tab menus and the different managers. The menus serve
	as entry points to the actions available from different
	contexts, while the managers let you check the state and control
	the various subsystems, such as loaded cookies and the global
	history. The utility menus and the manager tools are
	investigated further below.

</t>
<t>

	The document viewer in ELinks provides a feature-rich set of
	ways to browse documents. That is, multiple options exist for
	navigating, searching and displaying documents and you will
	hopefully figure in time what works best for you. The basic
	browsing possibilities are presented below.

</t>
<t>

	ELinks is highly configurable, so if there is something that you
	would like to change, it is most likely possible. The best
	overview of the many options are given in the elinks.conf(5) man
	page. Keybindings are discussed in the elinkskeys(5) man page.
	It is not always up-to-date, so you should also check the
	keybinding manager and the overview of all the configured
	keybindings given in the Help -> Keys dialog. The Keys dialogs
	serves as a good introduction to the most common keybindings.

</t>
</section>

<section title="The Title, Tab and Status bar">
<t>

	The title bars main purpose is to display the title of the
	current document.  Documents bigger than can be displayed with
	the current screen size are divided into subpages. In this case
	the current document position is indicated in the far right of
	the title bar as a suffix to the actual document title.  The
	syntax is: ( current-subpage / total-subpages ), an example is
	"(4/9)" that indicates the 4th subpage of 9 subpages.

</t>
<t>

	The tab bar by default is only visible when 2 or more tabs are
	open. It is divided into slots containing the trimmed title of
	the tabs' loaded document.  Between each tab is a separator. The
	current tab is highlighted and all tabs that has not been viewed
	after being loaded are highlighted as fresh.  Tabs are explained
	in details in the tabs.txt file.

</t>
<t>

	The status bar has multiple purposes. Most of the time it will
	contain the URI (and title) of the currently selected link. If a
	link is followed, connection information is shown in the status
	bar. When using cursor routing, the status bar will show the
	coordinates of the cursor when a link is not followed.

</t>
</section>

<section title="The Main, Link and Tab Menus">
<t>

	The Main Menu gives you access to many of the features of ELinks
	via submenus and serves as a good entry point for performing
	actions on the different objects of interest, such as links,
	documents and tabs. The Link menu and Tab menus are more
	specialized and targeted to a specific context, such as link
	handling or managing the tab bar. Actually, the Link Menu is
	accessible from the Main Menu as a submenu.

</t>
<t>

	Once you have familiarized yourself with the menus, you will
	have a good chance at gradually learning the most common
	keybinding, since all the configured keybindings are shown as
	right aligned text. Menu entries can also be quickly accessed
	using hotkeys. Hotkeys appear highlighted in the menu entry
	text. For example the key-combo "Alt-v i" will open the document
	info dialog accessible from the View sub menu in the Main menu.

</t>
</section>

<section title="The Managers">
<t>

	The managers let you control the state of subsystems, such as
	cookies and the global history. They are accessible from the
	Tools or Setup submenu in the Main Menu. The managers consists
	of an area showing a hierarchic listbox and buttons at the
	bottom. Below, a view of the cookie manager is shown.

</t>
<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork><![CDATA[
+------------------------- Cookie manager -------------------------+
|                                                                  |
|   [-]- bugzilla.elinks.or.cz                                     |
|    |    |-- BUGLIST                                              |
|    |    `-- LASTORDER                                            |
|   [+]- kerneltrap.org                                            |
|   [+]-*dictionary.reference.com                                  |
|   [+]-*bjork.com                                                 |
|   [-]- www.google.com                                            |
|         `-- PREF                                                 |
|                                                                  |
|                                                                  |
|                                                                  |
|                                                                  |
|   [ Info ]  [ Add ]  [ Edit ]  [ Delete ]  [ Save ]  [ Close ]   |
+------------------------------------------------------------------+]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>

	Each item is either a folder or a leaf. A folder is displayed
	with a "[-]" or "[+]" before the name telling whether the folder
	is currently open or closed. Nested items are displayed indented
	compared to the folder they are nested in. In the cookie manager
	example above "bjork.com" is a folder and "PREF" is a leaf.

</t>
<t>

	Items can be "marked", which makes it possible to select a group
	of items and perform an action on them, such as deleting all
	marked items. If any item has been marked the currently selected
	item is ignored when performing the action.  Marked items are
	displayed with an asterics ('*') prefixing the name.

</t>
<t>

	The buttons make it possible to perform actions either on
	selected or marked items or on all items in the manager. Buttons
	named "Clear" and "Save" are performed on all items; "Clear"
	will delete all items and "Save" will update the runtime state
	file associated with the manager in the ~/.elinks/ directory.
	Most buttons presses will query you before completing the
	action.

</t>
<t>

	At any time, both the currently selected item and button are
	highlighted. The same goes for marked items. Most manager
	dialogs also maintains the state, so that when you reopen the
	manager later it will have the same items selected and the same
	folders opened or closed.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>
	
	The basic default controls for managers are the following:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>Keys</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>Action</ttcol>

	<c>Up/Down</c>		<c>Select the item above/below.</c>
	<c>'*'</c>		<c>Toggle marking of a item.</c>
	<c>Space</c>		<c>Open and close folders.</c>
	<c>Left/Right</c>	<c>Select the button to the left/right.</c>
	<c>Home/End</c>		<c>Select the first/last item.</c>
	<c>Enter</c>		<c>Press the currently selected button.</c>
	<c>Esc</c>		<c>Close the manager dialog.</c>

<postamble></postamble>
</texttable>
<t>

	Some managers also supports searching, either by pressing the "[
	Search ]" button or by pressing '/'. By searching the empty
	string, all hidden items from the previous search will be shown
	again.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Navigation">
<t>

	ELinks provides various ways to navigate documents. Depending on
	how documents are structured, it can be a great help to change
	navigation style. The navigation styles can roughly be divided
	into page-oriented, link-oriented and screen-oriented. They
	overlap in many ways, so this separation is mostly used as a
	mean to present them.

</t>

<section title="Page-Oriented Navigation">
<t>

	This involves scrolling documents horizontally and vertically.
	Documents can be scrolled page-wise, where the next or previous
	subpage will be displayed. It is also possible to scroll documents in
	steps, either line-wise (vertically) or column-wise (horizontally).
	The step size can be configured and by default is 2 lines and 8
	columns. Alternatively, whole documents can be scrolled to the start
	or the end.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>
	
	The basic default controls:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>Keys</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>Action</ttcol>

	<c>Insert/Delete</c>	<c>Scroll up/down line-wise. (vertically)</c>
	<c>PageUp/PageDown</c>	<c>Scroll up/down page-wise.</c>
	<c>'['/']'</c>		<c>Scroll left/right column-wise. (horizontally)</c>
	<c>Home/End</c>		<c>Scroll to the start/end of the document.</c>

<postamble></postamble>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Link-Oriented Navigation">
<t>

	For hypertext documents, access to the links makes it more practical
	to navigate by jumping between links in the document. There are two
	ways to do this; either you can move between links relationally or by
	number. Using relational link navigation it is possible to focus the
	next/previous link or move in a directional manner to the link in a
	certain direction such as left/right/up/down.

</t>
<t>

	In order to navigate using link numbers, you have to first toggle link
	numbering on; this will prefix all links with a number using the
	notation [number]. "[23]" indicates link number 23. When link
	numbering is enabled, pressing any number key will pop up a "Go to
	link"-dialog where the complete link number can be entered. By
	pressing Enter the entered link number will be focused, but only if it
	is a valid link number.

</t>
<t>

	Note: it is also possible to jump to links by searching the link text;
	check the documentation on searching.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>
	
	The basic default controls:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>Keys</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>Action</ttcol>

	<c>Up/Down</c>		<c>Move to the previous/next link.</c>
	<c>'.'</c>		<c>Toggle link numbering.</c>
	<c>Enter/Right</c>	<c>Follow the current focused link.</c>

<postamble>

	No keys are by default configured for directional link
	navigation.

</postamble>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Position-Oriented Navigation">
<t>

	Positional navigation (sorry, bad word) uses the either the position
	of the cursor or the mouse click to navigate the document. If you are
	familiar with the w3m text-browser you will be familiar with cursor
	routing. Basicly, you move the cursor around -- kind of like a mouse --
	in the document area of the user interface. When the cursor is over a
	link, the link is highlighted, and when the cursor moves outside the
	current document view, it will cause the document view to scroll.

</t>
<t>

	The possibilities when using the mouse to navigate the document depend on
	what terminal you are using. In some terminals, it is possible to
	scroll by using the mouse wheel. Scrolling is however also possible by
	clicking in the edge areas of the document view. Highlighting links
	can be done by clicking on a link but waiting to release the mouse
	button until the link is no longer under the mouse pointer.

</t>
<t>

	No keys are by default configured for cursor routing.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Forms">
<t>

	The status bar will indicate the type and name of the field.

</t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Input text/Password fields:">

	These will be displayed as "________".

	Note that passwords will be obscured using "*" characters.
	Status bar will display something like "Text field, name q",
	or "Password field, name password" for password fields.

</t>
<t hangText="Textarea boxes:">

	These will be displayed as multiple lines consisting of "_".
	Status bar will display something like "Text area, name comment"

</t>
<t hangText="Buttons:">

	These will be displayed as "[ Go ]".
	Status bar will display something like "Submit form to ...",
	"Post form to ..." for submit buttons.

</t>
<t hangText="Checkboxes:">

	These will be displayed as "[ ]" or "[X]".
	Status bar will display something like "Checkbox, name c, value 1".
	To set one just press ENTER on it.

</t>
<t hangText="Radio buttons:">

	These will be displayed as "( )" or "(X)".
	Status bar will display something like "Radio button, name radio1".
	To set one, you may use ENTER.

</t>
<t hangText="Select lists:">

	These will be displayed as "[first item____]".
	Note that if multiple attribute is used, these are displayed as a
	group of checkboxes instead.
	Status bar will display something like "Select field, name list"
	To select one entry, press ENTER, then navigate using UP/DOWN, then
	press ENTER again.

</t>
</list>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Searching">
<t>

	Searching is by default available by pressing '/'. This will
	open a search dialog with a input text field for entering the
	search terms and checkboxes to control how searching is
	performed. You can indicate whether matching should be case
	sensitive and whether regular expressions or normal searching
	should be used.

</t>
<t>

	It is also possible to make an incremental search, also called
	type-ahead searching. You can search either the whole document
	text or only link text.  The latter can be useful if you see a
	link deep inside a page and want to get to it quickly.

</t>
<t>

	Matches of the search term will be high-lighted. After having
	performed document text search all matches will be high-lighted.
	To get rid of this high-lighting you have to ``search for the
	empty string'', that is open a search dialog and just press
	Enter in the input field.

</t>
<t>

	Previous search words are saved in the search history, so they
	can easily b found and used later. Browsing the history will
	replace the current entered search terms.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>

	The basic default controls for searching are the following:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>keys</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>action</ttcol>

	<c>'/'</c>	<c>Open search dialog</c>
	<c>'?'</c>	<c>Open search dialog for backwards searching</c>
	<c>'#'</c>	<c>Start incremental link text search</c>
	<c>'#/'</c>	<c>Start incremental document search</c>
	<c>'n'/'N'</c>	<c>Show next/previous match</c>
	<c>Tab</c>	<c>Show next match (only for incremental searching)</c>
	<c>Up/Down</c>	<c>Insert previous/next search word from history
			(only when the input field is selected)</c>
		
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Hints and Odd Features">
<t>

Note: This is still a work in progress and from here on an below
everything is marked TODO!

</t>
<list style="symbols">

	<t>Numerical action prefixes. Example: 3&lt;Down&gt; jumps down
		three links.</t>

	<t>How to move forward in the document history ('u').</t>

	<t>Toggling color modes, plain/html and image link rendering.</t>

	<t>Link numbering.</t>

	<t>Insert mode in text-input form-fields.</t>

	<t>Menu searching.</t>

</list>
</section>

</section>
