<section title="Managing External Viewers with Mailcap">
<t>

	This document describes the support for Mailcap (RFC 1524) in
	ELinks. It does not describe the mailcap format. There are
	plenty of documents on the Web that does this. Google and thou
	wilt find. ;)

</t>

<section title="A Short Intro to Mailcap">
<t>

	Mailcap is a file format defined in RFC 1524. Its purpose is to
	inform multiple mail reading user agent (MUA) programs about the
	locally-installed facilities for handling mail in various
	formats. It is designed to work with the Multipurpose Internet
	Mail Extensions, known as MIME.

</t>
<t>

	ELinks allows MIME handlers to be defined using its own
	configuration system, so why support mailcap? It can be seen as
	an alternative or simply as a supplement for setting up MIME
	handlers in ELinks.  Mailcap files are present on most UNIX
	systems--usually in /etc/mailcap--so this makes it possible for
	ELinks to know how to handle a great variety of file formats
	with little configuration. To be able to use mailcap, it has to
	be compiled into ELinks.  This is the default. If you don't need
	mailcap support, just configure ELinks with the flag:
	--disable-mailcap.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Parameters to Mailcap Entries">
<t>

	The code has been ported from Mutt and thereby inherits some of
	its various features and limitation.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>

	The following parameters are supported:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='20%' align='left'>Parameter</ttcol>
<ttcol width='80%' align='left'>Description</ttcol>

	<c>%s	</c><c>The filename that contains the data.</c>
	<c>%f	</c><c>The content type, like 'text/plain'.</c>

<postamble>
</postamble>
</texttable>
<texttable>
<preamble>

	The following parameters are not supported, since they do not
	really make much sense for a non-MUA program:

</preamble>
<ttcol width='20%' align='left'>Parameter</ttcol>
<ttcol width='80%' align='left'>Description</ttcol>

	<c>%n		</c><c>The integer number of sub-parts in the multipart</c>
	<c>%F		</c><c>The "content-type filename" repeated for each sub-part</c>
	<c>%{parameter}	</c><c>The "parameter" value from the content-type field</c>

<postamble>
</postamble>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Reading of Mailcap Files">
<t>

	Mailcap files will be read when starting ELinks. The mailcap
	files to use will be found from the mailcap path, a colon
	separated list of files similar to the $PATH environment
	variable. The mailcap path will be determined in the following
	way:

</t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>

	From the value of the mime.mailcap.path option in
	elinks.conf; for example:

<figure>
<artwork>
	  set mime.mailcap.path = "~/.mailcap:/usr/local/etc/mailcap"
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>

	From MAILCAP environment variable.

</t>
<t>

	If non of the above is defined, the mailcap path defaults to
	"~/.mailcap:/etc/mailcap".

</t>
</list>
</section>

<section title="Fields">
<t>

	Since mailcap handling is primarily for displaying of resources,
	all fields like edit, print, compose etc. are ignored.

</t>
<t>

	Note: Test commands are supported, but unfortunately, it's not
	possible to provide the file when running the test. So any test
	that requires a file will be considered failed and the handler
	will not be used.

</t>
<t>

	Unfortunately, there are no 'native' support for the
	copiousoutput field.  The field basically mean 'needs pager'. So
	it is handled by appending a pipe and a pager program to the
	command. The pager program will be read from the PAGER
	environment variable. If this fails, test are made for common
	pager programs (/usr/bin/pager, /usr/bin/less and /usr/bin/more
	in that order). So if you define png2ascii as your handler for
	image/png and specify copiousoutput then the executed command
	will be "png2ascii |/usr/bin/less" if less is your pager or
	present on your system.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Mailcap Configuration">
<t>

	Apart from the mime.mailcap.path option, you can configure if
	mailca support should be disabled. The default being that it is
	enabled. To disable it just put:

</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
	set mime.mailcap.enable = 0
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>

	in elinks.conf.

</t>
<t>

	It is also possible to control wether ELinks should ask you
	before opening a file. The option is a boolian and can be set
	like this:

</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
	set mime.mailcap.ask = 1
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>

	if you would like to be asked before opening a file.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Some Sample Mailcap Entries">
<figure>
<preamble>

	Below are examples of how to specify external viewers:

</preamble>
<artwork><![CDATA[
  # Use xv if X is running
  image/*;                xv %s ; test=test -n "$DISPLAY";

  # Convert images to text using the netpbm tools
  image/*;                (anytopnm %s | pnmscale -xysize 200 150 | \
       	                   pnminvert | ppmtopgm | pgmtopbm | \
       	                   pbmtoascii -1x2 ) 2>&1 ; copiousoutput

  # Various multimedia files
  audio/mpeg;             xmms '%s'; test=test -n "$DISPLAY";
  application/pdf;        xpdf '%s'; test=test -n "$DISPLAY";
  application/postscript; ps2ascii %s ; copiousoutput
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</section>
</section>
