<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="resources"><title>Miscellaneous information</title>

<sect1><title>Online Ressources</title>
<para>

	There are several ways to get more info on ELinks online.  You might
	consider to subscribe to one of the mailinglists or join the irc
	channel.

</para>

<sect2 id="homepage"><title>ELinks Homepage</title>
<para>

	The ELinks homepage can be found at <ulink
	url="http://elinks.or.cz/"></ulink>.  Here you'll find the newest
	releases available for download.

</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mailinglists"><title>Mailinglists</title>
<para>

	There are three mailinglists you may consider to subscribe to if you
	want to stay informed about what is going on.

</para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	<term><varname>links-list</varname></term>
	<listitem>
	<para>

		Releases are announced on this mailing list.  Else it is a
		low-traffic list mostly intended to questions from users and
		bugreports.
		
	</para>
	<para>

		For info about how to subcribe visit <ulink
		url="http://links.sf.net/mailing.html">
		http://links.sf.net/mailing.html</ulink>.
		
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term><varname>links-discuss</varname></term><listitem>
	<para>

		This is the place for discussing the development of ELinks.
		Make feature requests or send patches for language updates or
		new features.

	</para>
	<para>

		For info about how to subcribe visit <ulink
		url="http://links.sf.net/mailing.html">
		http://links.sf.net/mailing.html</ulink>.

	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term><varname>links-cvs</varname></term><listitem>
	<para>

		For people interested in tracking the development more closely
		by getting notifications about CVS commits.  If you want to
		know what's actually going on and stay on the cutting edge, you
		are strongly recommended to subscribe.

	</para>
	<para>

		Simply mail to <email>links-cvs-subscribe@v.or.cz</email>
		(subject or content of the mail doesn't matter) and follow the
		instructions in the reply. If you don't receive any reply
		within about an hour, please send a mail to
		<email>pasky@ucw.cz</email>. Note that in the public CVS mirror
		these changes may first appear up to 15minutes later.

	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Irc Channel</title>
<para>

	If you have a question and need a quick reply or just want to meet
	ELinks developers alive you can join the <varname>#elinks</varname>
	channel on <varname>irc.openprojects.org</varname>.

</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="bugreporting"><title>Bugreporting</title>
<epigraph><para>

	If it breaks you get to keep both pieces.

</para></epigraph>
<para>

	However if that happens we would very much like to hear about it. Send
	a detailed bugreport and we might even be able to fix it.

</para>
<para>

	Here is described how to submit a usefull bugreport.

</para>
<para>

	By reporting bugs you help us very much. We appreciate your help!

</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
