<section title="The Terminal Setup">
<t>

	ELinks uses neither (n)curses nor termcap/terminfo, so unless
	you are using a terminal that is known by ELinks and have a
	built-in configuration (see below for a list), it might be
	required that you do a little configuring of how your terminal
	should be handled. The easiest way to do this is using the
	Terminal Options dialog located in the Setup submenu of the Main
	menu.

</t>
<t>

	It is possible to have configurations for multiple terminals as
	long as the TERM environment variable -- used to distinguish
	terminals from one another -- is set to something different for
	each terminal. So be sure to set TERM to different values for
	two terminals that cannot share the same configuration.  For
	example, always setting TERM to xterm-color can lead to problems
	if you run ELinks under the Linux console. This is because the
	Linux console does not support underlining and ELinks will not
	know that underlined characters will have to be color
	highlighted so they stand out.

</t>
<t>

	In short, ELinks does not use termcap or terminfo. ELinks uses
	$TERM, but only to distinguish between terminals in its own
	configuration. That is, you need only configure your terminal
	within ELinks: Go to the Setup menu and select Terminal Options.
	If $TERM is set to 'screen' when you configure ELinks' terminal
	settings, ELinks will remember to use those settings when $TERM
	is 'screen'.

</t>

<section title="Options">
<t>

	Apart from the last charset option configurable through the
	Setup -> Character Set submenu in the Main menu, the rest can be
	configured using the Terminal Options dialog.

</t>

<section title="Terminal type">
<t>
		
	It maps roughly to the terminal type, such as Linux console,
	XTerm, VT100 etc. It matters mostly when drawing frames and
	borders around dialog windows. As already mentioned, it also
	turns on certain features which try to compensate for
	``missing'' terminal capabilities when drawing. Special
	highlighting of underlined text if underlining is not supported
	is one such thing.

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>
</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>Type</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>Notes</ttcol>

	<c>No frames		</c><c>Dumb terminal type / ASCII art</c>
	<c>VT 100 frames	</c><c>Works in most terminals</c>
	<c>Linux or OS/2 frames	</c><c>Linux console / you get double frames and other goodies</c>
	<c>KOI-8		</c><c></c>
	<c>FreeBSD		</c><c>FreeBSD console</c>

<postamble>

	The default is to assume dumb terminal/ASCII art.

</postamble>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Color mode">
<t>

	The color mode controls what colors are used and how they are
	output to the terminal. The available color modes are:

</t>
<texttable>
<preamble>
</preamble>
<ttcol width='30%' align='left'>Mode</ttcol>
<ttcol width='70%' align='left'>Color codes</ttcol>

	<c>Mono mode		</c><c>Only 2 colors are used</c>
	<c>16 color mode	</c><c>Uses the common ANSI colors</c>
	<c>256 color mode	</c><c>Uses XTerm RGB codes (if compiled in)</c>

<postamble>

	The default is to use mono mode.

</postamble>
</texttable>
</section>

<section title="Switch fonts for line drawing (aka 11m hack)">
<t>

	This is related to the drawing of frames and window borders
	controlled by the option above. It controls whether to switch
	fonts when drawing lines, enabling both local characters and
	lines working at the same time.

</t>
<t>

	This boolean option only makes sense with the Linux terminal.  Off
	off by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Restrict frames in cp850/852">
<t>

	This is related to the drawing of frames and window borders
	controlled by the option above. If enabled, it restricts the
	characters used when drawing lines.

</t>
<t>

	This boolean option only makes sense with the Linux terminals
	using the cp850/852 character sets. Off by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Block cursor">
<t>

	Move cursor to bottom right corner when done drawing if
	possible. This is particularly useful when we have a block
	cursor, so that text colors are displayed correctly. If you are
	using a screen reader you do not want to enable it since the
	cursor is strategically positioned near relevant text of
	selected dialog elements.

</t>
<t>

	This boolean option is off by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Transparency">
<t>

	Whether to set the background to black. This is particularly
	useful when using a terminal (typically in some windowing
	environment) with a background image or a transparent
	background. If this option is enabled the background will be
	visible in ELinks as well.

</t>
<t>

	Note that this boolean option makes sense only when colors are
	enabled. On by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Text underlining capability">
<t>

	This boolean option controls whether to underline text or
	enhance the color instead.

</t>
<t>

	Note: not all terminals support text underlining, so it is off
	by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="UTF-8 I/O">
<t>

	This boolean option controls outputting of I/O in UTF-8 for
	Unicode terminals.

</t>
<t>

	Note that currently, only the subset of UTF-8 according to the
	terminal codepage is used. Offff by default.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Character Set">
<t>

	Codepage of the charset used for displaying content on terminal.

</t>
<t>

	The value 'System' (which is the default) will set the charset
	according to the current locale. The default is to use the
	charset of the current locale.

</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Terminal Configurations">
<t>

	Built-in configurations exists for the following terminals:

</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
		linux, vt100, vt110, xterm, xterm-color and xterm-256color
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>

	The last configuration requires that support for 256 is compiled in.

</t>
<t>

	GNU Screen is VT100-compatible, so select 'VT 100 frames'. GNU
	Screen also supports colors just fine, so select '16 colors'; or
	if you are running Screen within a terminal emulator that
	supports 256 colors and you have compiled both Screen and ELinks
	to support it, choose '256 colors'.

</t>
</section>
</section>
